台灣紅燒牛肉麵做法收集/冠軍牛肉麵做法

2011年得奬冠軍的 台灣紅燒牛肉麵作法 侯圳生師傅 舊金山巡迴示範

紅燒牛肉麵冠軍的侯圳生師傅
為了推廣台灣美食，行政院新聞局特邀請去年11月榮獲「台北國際牛肉麵節」紅燒組冠軍的侯圳生師傅，於2月4日至13日至舊金山展示他的廚藝，並公布他得獎牛肉麵的食譜秘方。
經駐舊金山辦事處新聞組的數月安排，侯師傅將於2月8日中午在Google矽谷總公司、同日晚舊金山L’Olivier法國餐廳、2月9日 下午在沙加緬度Spataro義大利餐廳，以及2月11日中午在全美高級廚具連鎖店Williams-Sonoma舊金山旗艦店等4場地巡迴示範他冠軍作 品，隨後轉赴華府，讓美國人品嚐義大利麵、越南麵及日本拉麵以外的另一種的麵食天地。
侯師傅現年48歲，嘉義人。他自民國67年7月在台北西門町當學徒以來，在台灣南北各大城擔任廚師，廚藝經歷豐富。「台北國際牛肉麵節」為 台北市政府主辦，迄今已舉辦7屆，為台灣一年一度的牛肉麵盟主爭霸賽，名聞遐邇。身為西餐師傅的他，為了參賽，花了3年時間觀察及研發。去年2011年第一次 參加此一擂台盛會，一舉奪冠。侯師傅掌廚的Room 18夜店，原本不賣中餐，侯師傅得獎牛肉麵推出後熱賣，反成該店招牌菜。
台灣美食不勝枚舉，為何選中牛肉麵？負責策劃侯師傅訪問舊金山的駐舊金山辦事處新聞組組長彭滂沱表示，牛肉麵是1949年大陸移民在台獨 創，在台灣生根後成為在地美食，隱然有族群融合的意義。如今牛肉麵為台灣民眾的日常簡餐，也是高級大飯店的豪華佳餚，價位可從新台幣100元到新台幣1萬 美元，是台灣最經典的全民餐點。
牛肉麵特色之一為簡單易煮。但是，侯師傅創意十足的冠軍作品可不然。新聞組上上下下的同仁為了規劃代購侯師傅的食材，實做多次，結果與真味仍有距離。
冠軍紅燒牛肉麵作法
以下是侯師傅的中文食譜

材料： 牛腱 2.25磅 、 牛骨 2.25磅 青蔥 6 隻 （2隻切蔥花備用）、 蒜仁 12-14 粒 、拍碎 老薑 切薄片 二英吋 約拇指寬大小、 紅辣椒1條 對半切 蘿蔓萵苣 （約1磅）切片 （台灣小白菜、空心菜也可） 牛蕃茄 大的2個 ，去皮，切成.25“立方體 
植物油 4湯匙 為煸炒用 黑胡椒粒 1湯匙（約1盎司） 月桂葉 2大片、冰糖1湯匙（約1盎司） 辣豆瓣醬 3/4杯（4oz）、 辣豆腐乳 1/2杯（5oz)、 金蘭醬油 1杯（10oz）、 金蘭油膏 4個半湯匙、 廣東老抽 2個半湯匙 （約130盎司） 最好是李錦記 蕃茄糊 1 /4杯 （不到2盎司） 台灣香菜 1 /4杯 （不到2盎司） 家常拉麵 自選 中藥香料包 2個。

中藥包： 八角1錢、 茴香1錢 、當歸1錢、陳皮1錢 (0.8g) 花椒3錢、桂子3錢、桂皮3錢、桂枝3錢（2.5g) (以上為40人份計量，請依實際人數等量調整)

作法：
1. 將美國牛腱心煮熟待冷後，切約1公分厚-備用。
（牛骨高湯）
2. 牛骨加冷水煮開 ---撈去雜質後-備用。
3. 熱鍋入1/2油將青蔥1/2、老薑1/2、蒜仁1/2、紅辣椒1/2炒到香味出來, 再加冰糖、豆瓣醬、醬油ㄧ半略煮，放入牛骨湯中再加中藥包、月桂葉、黑胡椒粒ㄧ半、豆腐乳ㄧ半、蕃茄糊煮約6小時。
(醬牛腱肉)
4.熱鍋入1/2油將青蔥1/2、老薑1/2、蒜仁1/2、紅辣椒炒到香味出來,
加冰糖、豆瓣醬、醬油略煮，放入切好的牛腱心片再加剩下另一半豆腐乳、金蘭油膏、廣東老抽、中藥包、月桂葉、黑胡椒粒，加入大量足夠的水、以中小火煮約30分鐘後熄火燜放到冷卻。
撈出牛肉塊、如果你想要更濃的醬湯、可繼續再中大火煮滾濃縮！
（準備麵條和配菜）
5.牛蕃茄去皮切成1公分小丁， 切蘿蔓萵苣小片， 切蔥花。備用！
6.(牛骨高湯)5分之4和（醬牛腱原汁）5分之1混和加入蕃茄丁備用。
7.水煮開放麵煮熟撈起去水，再燙熟蘿蔓萵苣。
8.熟麵條放入碗中再放上牛腱心片再倒入混合好的牛肉湯，加入燙過蘿蔓萵苣生菜、蕃茄丁及蔥花即完成。
＊搭配炒過的酸菜更棒！ 
yoyo
中英文對照後, 再以食譜內容文字略微增添
但不影響到大師的原味！
以上僅供yoyo自我料理時的參考資料！

出處  舊金山經文處中文版
http://www.roc-taiwan.org/US//ct.asp?xItem=250993&ctNode=2982&mp=66
Beef Noodle Soup
The recipe has been modified to serve 10 large bowls.  As in many Taiwanese food recipes, the measurement of the ingredients varies, depending on your experience and personal taste. In addition, the special herbs are not easy to find outside Chinatown.

Ingredients

2.25 lbs boneless beef shanks
2.25 lbs beef bones, pieces
4 tbsp vegetable oil for sauteing
6 green onions, 4 roughly chopped into 3」 for stock and sauce, 2 stalks finely sliced for topping
12-14 garlic cloves, smashed
2 inches ginger, sliced (not too think or thick)
1 red hot chili peppers, halved
1 tbsp rock sugar (about 1 oz)
¾ cup hot bean paste (or around 4 oz)
1 cup soy sauce, preferably Kimlan
½ cup spicy fermented bean curd (or around 5 oz)
¼ cup tomato paste (just under 2 oz)
1 tbsp black peppercorn (around 1 oz)
2 Bay leaves, large (depending on size)
4 ½ tbsp soy paste, preferably Kimlan (around 2 oz)
2 ½ tbsp dark soy sauce, preferably Lee Kum Kee (around 1.3 oz)
1 head of Romaine lettuce, chopped into 1」 slices (roughly 1 lbs)
2 large beefsteak tomatoes, peeled and chopped into .25」 cube
¼ cup cilantro, (optional topping)
2 Chinese herb bags: contains one part (.8 gram each) of Star Anise (pa-chiao), Fennel (huei-hsiang), Angelica roots (tang-kuei), and dried orange peel (cheng-pi); as well as three parts (2.5 grams each) of Pericarpium Zanthoxyli (hua-chiao), Cassia buds (kuei-tze), Cinnamon peel/bark (kuei-pi), and Cinnamon stick (kuei-chi). (The Chinese herbal shop uses a measurement system that does not have an English equivalent, however we converted it to the metric system to give you a better idea of the quantities involved.)
Fresh noodle, depending on your preference and what's available locally
Preparing the broth
1) Boil about 1 gallons of water and beef bones and filter out impurities.
2) Heat half of the oil and saute half of the green onions, ginger, garlic and red hot chilly peppers until you get a nice fragrant smell. Add half of the rock sugar, hot bean paste, soy sauce to the vegetables and cook slightly before combining it to the beef bone broth.
3) Then add half the fermented bean curd and all the tomato paste.
4) Lastly, include half of the the black peppercorn, bay leaves and one Chinese seasoning bag to the broth.
5) Simmer for 6 hours. If you are not using a mesh herb bag, be sure to put the broth through a sieve.
Preparing the beef shank
1) Cook the beef shank with just enough water to cover the meat, boil the meat until it's cooked through. Let it cool and then sliced into oval disks, about one-third inch thick. Save the beef water for later.
2) Sauté the remaining green onions, ginger, garlic and red hot chili peppers in vegetable oil until it's fragrant. Add theremaining rock sugar, hot bean paste and soy sauce, cook briefly.
3) Add the remaining fermented bean curd, and all the soy paste and dark soy sauce, before adding the rest of the black peppercorn, bay leaf and Chinese herb packet.
4) Place the sliced beef shanks into the sauce and add just enough beef water to cover the beef slices. Stir to ensure even mixing. Cover and cook for 30 minutes. If you like your meat more tender, you can cook for longer. Keep the pot covered while it's cooling down. Take the slices out and strain the remaining liquid if you want a smoother sauce.
Preparing the noodle and assembling the dish 
1) Boil the water, add the noodle and cook until done. Drain.
2) Remove the skin from the tomatoes, and chop them into ¼ inch cubes. (You can peel tomatoes easily by dropping it into boiling water for a few seconds. The skin will separate from the flesh. Take it out and dip into cold water)
3) Chop the Romaine lettuce into 1 inch shreds. Then flash cook the lettuce in boiling water. Drain.
4) Put noodles into the bowl, top with beef shanks, lettuce, tomatoes, and spoon 4/5 beef broth, 1/5 beef sauce. Top with chopped green onions and cilantro. Enjoy.
冠軍牛肉麵做法, 台灣紅燒牛肉麵做法
＜紅燒牛肉麵做法＞
材料：肋條5斤、洋蔥1個、紅辣椒1根、大蒜5粒、生薑片8片、青蔥4根、滷包1個。調味料：辣豆瓣醬2大匙、醬油1湯匙、胡椒粉適量、米酒1湯匙。
做法：
1.牛肉切成5公分見方的肉塊。
2.洋蔥切絲；紅辣椒、青蔥切段；大蒜、生薑切片；番茄切塊，備用。
3.牛肉放入滾水汆燙去血水後，另煮一鍋水，放入適量蔥段、薑片及滷包，水滾後（水量剛剛能淹過材料），將汆過水的肉塊放入，落米酒，待水開之後，讓肉塊稍煮一下，即可起鍋，湯汁留用。
4.起油鍋，陸續放下洋蔥、紅辣椒、青蔥、大蒜、生薑、番茄翻炒，然後放下牛肉塊和豆瓣醬，拌炒均勻。
5.將煮過牛肉的湯汁和滷包一起倒入材料中，加醬油、胡椒粉調味，先煮到滾沸，蓋上鍋蓋，轉小火紅燒兩個半小時。
＜清燉牛肉麵做法＞
材料：半筋半肉5斤、芹菜一支、薑6片、蔥2支、米酒1湯匙。
牛骨高湯：選用牛的龍骨，汆燙，洗淨浮沬。
另起一鍋滾水，放1粒八角、薑、蔥、米酒及牛骨一起熬高湯，先用大火將水滾開，而後關小，維持菊花火狀態燉兩小時。

紅燒牛肉麵做法 (梁幼祥食譜)
1. 將買來的整塊牛肋條或是牛腱(約兩斤)入鍋，加水，加蔥兩支，薑六片，米酒一湯匙，煮20分鐘。
（牛肉不能先過水，而且要從冷水慢慢加熱至沸騰後轉小火，中間也不能加冷水，一鍋到底血水是美味的來源，只要去掉表面的雜質即可牛肉撈起後）
2. 將肉撈出，切自己喜歡的大小塊或是片狀。做法2之前千萬別切肉，因為肉尚未成型，切成小塊再煮再燉，肉會變得歪七扭八的不美觀。
3. 在炒鍋中放四匙油，炒香20粒大蒜、一個洋蔥切片、2湯匙花椒，待洋蔥軟香，加入三湯匙辣豆辦醬、醬油一杯、糖一湯匙、酒三湯匙，用中小火拌炒一分鐘(可以加番茄一個，也可以不加)。
4. 將牛肉及原來煮牛肉的湯一起入鍋，並加入六粒八角、兩片月桂葉及少許胡椒粉，煮滾後用文火續煮一小時，關火蓋上鍋蓋，不要動鍋中物，一直等到鍋冷就成了。
再加熱時，再試味道加鹽調味，即成牛肉湯底了！
上述的(泡)是牛肉好吃的秘訣
許多市面上牛肉麵店都不懂這個道理，牛肉的爛是用泡出來的而不是一直燉出來的，這是我三十年的秘方。
(被唐湘龍逼的寫在網路上，傳家寶沒了，我的帳全找他算，但朋友們請盡情分享)
真正好吃的牛肉，是要看起來堅挺，而吃起來柔嫩軟塌，還要帶著膠質，微微的會沾唇才過癮. 如果你吃的牛肉 少了這個膠質的口感，基本上是師傅對於牛肉的質地見解還不夠。
這燉煮牛肉的手法提供給所有愛煮牛肉麵的朋友及賣牛肉麵的店家們，更提供給那些評判牛肉麵比賽的裁判作為參考。
如果要做清燉的牛肉湯，則只放八角及花椒即可，其餘手法一樣。

台灣紅燒牛肉麵

材料： 牛腩 1kg 蕃茄(大) 1顆 白蘿蔔 1/2條 蔥 2支 老薑 數片 大蒜 5粒 八角 少 1-2 牛肉滷包1-2個 拉麵 適量 青菜 適量 酸菜 適量 蔥花 適量

醃料： 辣豆瓣醬 3tbsp 醬油 1/2杯 冰糖 少許

做法： 
1.先將牛腩、蕃茄、紅白蘿蔔切塊，蔥切段，大蒜拍碎備用。 
2.煮一鍋熱水將牛腩汆燙過後，以水邊沖邊用手壓牛腩，將血水擠出一直到沒有血水出來，瀝乾置於一旁。 
3.鍋內放入沙拉油，中火爆香薑蒜後，加入牛腩不停拌炒，陸續加入辣豆瓣醬、醬油，使牛腩上色、辣味出現。 
4.在鍋中加入高湯，以略為蓋過牛腩為準，並將蕃茄、紅白蘿蔔、八角、蔥、冰糖、滷包加入湯中 
5.大火煮開撈除泡沫，轉小火煮至牛腩軟爛入味即為紅燒牛肉湯。 
6.將麵條煮熟，倒入牛肉湯，加上蔥花、燙青菜、酸菜即可食用